So at the end of each week, it's customary for me to give you a challenge, an assignment to do on
매주 끝날 때마다 도전 과제를 드리는 게 관례예요 혼자 해내야
your own.
하죠
And there's been some interesting assignments I hope you agree that we've had so far, but let me just
여러분도 동의하시길 바라며 흥미로운 과제들이 있었지만 이번 주에 공개할게요 Tudum
put it out there this week.
Tudum Tudum
The assignment is by far the most interesting so far, and I really, really hope you take this one
이번 과제가 지금까지 중 가장 흥미로워요 다들 이번 과제를 진지하게 받아들이고
seriously and give it a good crack, because I'm going to do it myself too.
열심히 해 주길 바라요 나도 직접 할 거니까요
And I challenge you to it because I want to do this as quickly as I can.
이의를 제기합니다 최대한 빨리 끝내고 싶거든요
I think it's going to make an amazing blog post.
멋진 post가 될 것 같아요
I think it's going to be something that's that's really cool and really fun.
정말 멋지고 재미있는 일이 될 것 같아요
So here's the challenge.
문제는 이거예요
Take exactly what we've just built and use it to build your own knowledge worker on your own information
방금 만든 걸 이용해 개인 생산성을 높이기 위해 여러분의 정보에 기반한 여러분의
as a way to boost your own personal productivity.
지식 작업자를 만드는 거죠
So, for example, you could assemble all of your files that you've got in one place, and maybe you
예를 들어 한 곳에 있는 모든 파일을 조립할 수 있어요 이미 하드 드라이브에
already have that on your hard drive, I certainly do.
있을 수도 있죠 전 그래요
And so then that is effectively your own personal knowledge base with a folder structure.
폴더 구조가 있는 여러분의 개인적 지식 기반이죠
You can then vectorize everything in chroma, which will then become your own personal vector data store,
모든 걸 크로마로 벡터화할 수 있어요 그럼 여러분 고유의 벡터 데이터 저장소가 되죠 그
and you can then build a conversational AI on top of it and ask questions about your information.
위에 대화용 인공지능을 만들어 여러분의 정보에 관해 질문할 수 있어요
And when I think about the amount of information I have about projects I've worked on, about things
제가 작업했던 프로젝트와 했던 일에 대한 정보의 양을 생각해 보면
that I've done, there's no way I've got that in my mind.
제 마음속에 그런 게 있을 리가 없어요
Like, I spend so much of my time digging things up, and the idea that I'd be able to have a a chatbot
뭔가를 파헤치는 데 많은 시간을 보내는데 제 개인적인 배경에 최적화된
that is optimized for my own personal background, perhaps bringing together both the my work and personal
챗봇을 만들 생각을 하니 어쩌면 일과 개인적인 것을 합쳐서 연결할 수 있을지도
stuff so that I could really connect the dots.
몰라요
Think about someone that might be able to help me with a particular problem from across all of my contacts,
제 연락처, 현재 직장, 이전 직장 등에서 저를 도와줄 수 있는
current job, previous jobs, and so on.
누군가를 생각해 보세요.
It's just an amazingly powerful idea.
놀랍도록 강력한 아이디어예요
And so I'm very excited to do this myself.
그래서 직접 하게 돼서 정말 신나요
There's a couple of things that you could do to take it even further if you want to go really insane.
더 멀리 갈 수 있는 방법이 몇 가지 있어요 정말 미친 짓을 하고 싶다면요
And again, that's what I'm planning to do.
다시 말하지만 그게 제 계획이에요
So I use a Gmail, as does most of the internet, and it's reasonably easy to write some code so that
그래서 전 지메일을 써요 인터넷 대부분이 그렇죠 코드 작성하는 건 꽤 쉬워요 구글 API에
you can authenticate against the Google API and then have access to your own inbox to be able to read
대항해 인증을 하고 구글 API를 통해 이메일을 읽을 수 있는 자신의 메일함에 엑세스
your emails, uh, through Google's API.
권한을 가질 수 있죠
I say it's easy.
전 쉽다고 봐요
It's sort of medium easy.
중간 크기예요
Like the the code that they have to authenticate is a bit of a bore, but so many people have done it
인증해야 하는 코드는 좀 지루하지만 많은 사람들이 해 봐서 구글에 쉽게
that you can quite easily Google it and see step by step instructions for how to do it.
검색할 수 있어요 단계별로 어떻게 하는지 비트를 볼 수 있죠
So one could connect to one's email box and bring in emails and also vectorize them in Chrome.
이메일 상자에 접속해서 메일을 불러오고 크롬으로 벡터화할 수 있죠
So you would have your email history there too.
이메일 기록도 있을 거예요
Uh, obviously it's it's completely unrealistic to provide all of this context in some massive, uh,
물론 이 모든 맥락을 개척자 모델로 보여주는 건 완전히
context window to to to frontier model.
비현실적인 일이죠
You can hopefully imagine that all of your material would be bigger than the million tokens that even
모든 자재가 제미니 1호 토큰보다 훨씬 클 거라고 상상할 수
Gemini 1.5 flash can take.
있어요 5번 섬광도 견뎌요
But using Rag, it would be entirely possible to pluck out the 25 closest documents in your vector database
하지만 래그를 이용해 벡터 데이터베이스에서 특정 질문에 가장 가까운 25개의 문서를 뽑아내는 건 전적으로
to a particular question and then be able to provide them.
가능합니다 그리고 그걸 제공할 수 있죠
And so you could imagine you could do that for your email inbox.
이메일 받은 편지함에 그렇게 할 수 있다고 상상해 보세요
You could also do it for if you have Microsoft Office files.
마이크로소프트 Office 파일이 있다면 그렇게 할 수도 있어요
There are simple Python libraries that will read office files and bring out the text versions of them.
간단한 파이썬 라이브러리가 있습니다 Office 파일을 읽고 텍스트 버전으로 불러오죠
And if you use Google Drive, then Google has an API to be able to read your documents in Google Drive.
구글 드라이브를 사용한다면 구글 드라이브에 있는 문서를 읽을 API가 있어요
Again, not super easy.
아주 쉬운 일은 아니죠
There's a bit of hokey stuff to authenticate, but it's completely doable, and I really think that
감정할 게 좀 있지만 충분히 할 수 있어요 보상을 받으면 비트로도
the reward would make it worth it.
가치가 있죠
One final tiny point to this you might have a concern about calling things like OpenAI embeddings to
마지막으로 작은 포인트를 말씀드리면 오픈AI 엠베딩 같은 것을 호출해 모든 데이터를 벡터화하는
be vectorizing all of your data, because there's always a sense of, okay, so how confident are we
것을 우려할 수 있습니다 왜냐하면 항상 이런 느낌이 들거든요 개인 데이터로 호출하는
that these calls we're making with our private data isn't getting kept anywhere?
것이 아무 데도 저장되지 않을 거라고 얼마나 확신하나요?
Um, and so as a final part to this challenge, if that is something that's a concern for you, then
그래서 이번 과제의 마지막 부분으로 그게 걱정된다면
you can actually use an open source model like Bert to run it yourself.
버트 같은 오픈 소스 모델을 직접 활용해도 좋아요
You can do the vectorization yourself.
벡터화는 직접 할 수 있어요
And again, there's a couple of ways of doing it.
두 가지 방법이 있어요
The way that you know about is you could just bring up a Google Colab, you could have your Google Drive
여러분이 아는 방법은 구글 Colab을 불러올 수 있다는 겁니다 구글 드라이브를
mapped to that colab, and you can simply use that in Colab to be vectorizing all of your documents
그 Colab에 매핑할 수 있어요 그걸 Colab에서 이용해 모든 문서를 그런 식으로 벡터화할 수
that way.
있죠
So that's one way to do it.
그게 한 가지 방법이죠
That would be very effective.
아주 효과적일 거예요
Another way that's perhaps slightly more advanced is that you could use something called llama CP llama
좀 더 고급인 다른 방법은 llama CP llama.CP라는 걸 이용하는
dot CP, which is a library that you can run on your computer locally, and it has optimized C plus
겁니다 라이브러리인데 여러분 컴퓨터에서 로컬로 실행할 수 있죠 C++ 코드를 최적화해
plus code to run some of these models in inference mode locally on your box without ever leaving your
일부 모델을 추론 모드에서 여러분 박스에서 로컬로 실행합니다 여러분 박스를 떠나지 않고요
Um, and so that can be a final approach you could use if you wish to be able to vectorize all of your
클라우드로 가지 않고도 모든 문서를 벡터화하고 싶다면 이 방법을 최종적으로
documents without having to go to the cloud.
사용할 수 있어요
Um, but all in all, the challenge for you is make a personal, private knowledge worker for yourself
하지만 결국 가장 어려운 건 개인적이고 개인적인 지식인을 만들어서 할 수 있다는
to prove that you can do this.
걸 증명하는 거예요
And if that's too much of an endeavor for you, then at the very least, take a few text documents that
그게 너무 힘들다면 최소한 갖고 있는 텍스트 문서 몇 개를
you've got and drop them in the same folder to do a mini version of it.
같은 폴더에 넣어 축소판을 만드세요
At least do that.
그것만이라도 해 줘요
That is the minimum threshold.
그게 최소 기준치예요
I at least ask for that.
그 정도는 요구해야죠
Some text documents in that folder structure, so that you can see how this might work for your own
폴더 구조의 텍스트 문서를요 여러분 것을 위해 어떻게 작동하는지 볼 수 있도록요
stuff.
하지만 누군가 이 프로젝트를 실제로 해내면 좋겠어요
I'm going to do it too, and write a blog post about it, and I can't wait.
저도 할 거예요 블로그 post도 쓸 거고요 기대되네요
And that wraps up our week of Rag.
이것으로 래그 주간을 마칠게요
And at that point, it brings you to 62.5% of your way along this journey.
그 시점에서 62점이 되죠 5%밖에 못 갔어요
And I hope you feel that sense of upskilling.
의욕이 샘솟는 걸 느끼셨길 바라요
I hope you now feel so many things are coming together As long as you're doing these exercises and as
이제 많은 게 합쳐진다고 느끼길 바라요 이런 훈련을 계속하고
long as you are learning by doing at this point, you've got a great intuition for how rag works and
지금 이렇게 배우기만 한다면 래그가 어떻게 작동하고 왜 효과적인지 직관적으로
why it works and why it's effective.
알 수 있을 거예요
You understand about vector embedding and vector data stores, and all of that is in addition to everything
벡터 삽입과 벡터 데이터 저장소는 아실 겁니다 이 모든 것은 우리가 과거에 연구한 모든 것 외에도 프론티어
else we've worked on in the past working with frontier models, AI assistants, using tools, using
모델과 툴을 이용한 인공지능 조수들 오픈 소스 모델에 얼굴을 끌어안기 파이프라인 토큰라이저 모델에
hugging face for open source models, for pipelines tokenizers models, and also choosing the right
맞는 LLM을 선택하는 데에 기여했죠 다양한 leaderboard를 이용해 올바른 LLM을 선택하기도
LLM using the various leaderboards like the open LLM leaderboard from Hugging Face.
했습니다 페이스 포옹의 오픈 LLM leaderboard처럼요
So it's a big moment.
중요한 순간이죠
It's very exciting.
정말 신나요
Uh, but next week we start on something completely new.
하지만 다음 주에는 완전히 새로운 걸 시작해요
We're going to introduce a new commercial project.
새로운 상업 프로젝트를 소개할 거예요
We're going to download a dataset from Hugging Face, and we're going to be curating our data to take
얼굴 안기 게임 데이터셋을 다운로드 해서 데이터를 큐레이팅해 새롭고 흥미로운
on something new and exciting.
걸 시도할 거예요
That involves moving from the world of inference to the world of training, which is a very big step
추론만 하던 것을 훈련으로 바꾼 셈이니 큰 발전이죠
I can't wait, and I'll see you then.
기대되네요, 그때 봐요